"Are Large Weekly Doses of Vitamin B12 Safe?"
Serious adverse effects,
even with high doses
of injected vitamin B12
(hydroxocobalamin),
have never been reported.
However, some patients
do report acne breakouts
after high-dose injections,
which I talked about before.
But, hold on.
When you look
at the relationship
between B12 concentrations
in the blood and mortality,
you see graphs like this,
where having low levels
isn’t good,
with higher mortality,
but high levels in the blood
is associated
with higher mortality too.
What are some of the ways
we could get high B12 levels?
One could be
B12 supplementation,
but it could also be due to B12
being released
from damaged tissues
or not clearing as well
from malfunctioning kidneys-
in other words,
reverse causation.
Instead of high B12
causing disease,
disease is causing high B12.
How could we tease that out?
There is a correlation between
high blood B12 and cancer,
for example.
Which one might be leading
to the other?
Well, when you treat
the cancer,
when you shrink the tumors,
B12 levels drop,
suggesting that
the active tumor
was the source
of high vitamin B12 levels
in the circulation
instead of vice versa.
And that’s what you see
when you look
at other conditions:
the blood
B12 concentrations rise
as a consequence
of acute and chronic illness.
A cause-and-effect relationship
between serum
B12 concentrations
and subsequent disease
or mortality
has never been demonstrated.
In fact, how else can you get
lots of B12 in your system?
By eating lots of meat.
So, high B12 levels
may be a proxy in some cases
for increased intake of meat.
If you go back
and separate out the effects
of different sources of B12,
high intake of vitamin B12
in the form of supplements
was not associated with any
adverse effect on mortality
and, therefore, can be regarded
as safe.
And you see the same thing
when you look at the origin
of vitamin B12 levels
and mortality across the board
in a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of all such studies.
High blood concentrations
caused by dietary sources
of vitamin B12-meat,
eggs, and dairy-
may increase
all-cause mortality,
but when B12 levels are high
from supplement sources,
there doesn’t seem
to be a problem,
while higher mortality
associated
with cardiovascular disease
or obesity is associated
with higher intake
of foods like meat.
The bottom line
is that long-term studies
clearly indicate that treatment
with even high
pharmacological doses of B12
and the corresponding increase
in serum B12 levels
do not increase mortality risk.
"Supplemental forms of B12
are considered safe
and there is no evidence-based
Tolerable Upper Intake Level
for vitamin B12,"
because you just poop out
whatever you don’t absorb.
Remember, when you take
a single weekly megadose
of 2,000 micrograms of B12,
you only absorb
about 20 micrograms of it,
and the other 1,980 just get
flushed down the toilet.
But wait, before that happens,
that massive load of B12
hits our colon.
Might that be mucking
with our microbiome?
You think we need B12?
We only need it
for two enzymes,
whereas it’s required
for more than a dozen enzymes
in bacteria.
Only a minority
of the bacteria in our gut
may make it though,
yet the vast majority need it.
So, where do they get it?
They borrow it from a neighbor,
like going next door to get
a cup of flour or something.
We may have a thousand or more
difference species in our gut
and they share vitamins.
It’s like one big open bazaar
down there.
This is just to say that B12
is a big deal for bacteria
and may play
an unrecognized role
in shaping the structure
and function
of our microbiome.
Okay, but for good or for ill?
Vitamin B12 supplements
typically contain doses
that far exceed anything
we would naturally have seen
evolutionarily
and though it’s considered safe,
we know our gut bugs are
fighting over it all the time.
To what extent might
excessive levels affect us?
If mice are given
the human equivalent
of just 5,000 micrograms,
not much seems to happen
to their microbiomes.
But if they’re given
the equivalent
of 25,000 micrograms a day,
it accelerates the colonization
of a bad bug
called Citrobacter rodentium,
but as its name suggests,
it’s a mouse-specific pathogen.
It’s not a bug
you even see in humans.
But what about B12 in people?
To date, very few studies
have been done,
so the impact of vitamin B12
on our gut microbiome
has not been established.
And the studies we do have
are all over the place.
In this one,
B12 supplementation
in an in vitro
colonic stimulation-
basically, human feces
passed through a series
of beakers and tubes-
the B12 seemed to actually have
microbiome benefits.
Other similar-type studies
showed that B12
seemed to have
a more limited impact
not affecting bacterial growth,
richness, diversity,
or total metabolite production.
However, there was an increase
in propionate,
which is a beneficial
short-chain fatty acid.
In this study,
some beneficial bacteria
that produce
short-chain fatty acids
were reduced by B12,
but overall,
the amount of short-chain
fatty acids went up.
So, vitamin B12 supplementation
may actually be beneficial
for the gut
through interactions
with our microbiome.
So, while B12 injections are
often used for B12 deficiency,
those individuals
may be missing out
on microbiome benefits
of oral supplementation.
If anything, the potential risk
of giving larger weekly doses
versus smaller daily doses
would not be
from getting too much,
but from getting too little.
We’re counting on
that approximate 1% absorption
at higher doses,
however this passive absorption
may vary between individuals,
so if we instead only absorbed
half a percent
or a tenth of a percent,
we wouldn’t get enough dosing
once a week.
To boost absorption,
we can take high doses
on an empty stomach.
Instead of passively absorbing
about 1%
of a 500-microgram dose
when taken with a meal,
absorption is boosted
by about 60%
on an empty stomach.
Although the higher
weekly doses
have been proven
to improve B12 status
in deficient populations,
since we really don’t know
the long-term effects
of all that extra B12
hitting our colon,
an alternative would be
to get 2 or 2.5 micrograms
at each meal,
as I talked about
with fortified foods
in the last video.